Katie Louchheim Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
- Speeches and Writings File, circa 1937-1974 (Box 40-56)
  - Speeches
    - 1967
      - Nov. 21, National Council of Women of the United States, poetry reading, New York, N.Y.
      - Nov. 27, American Institute of Chemical Engineers, New York, N.Y.
      - Correspondence and miscellaneous speeches
    - 1968
      - Jan. 22, "Highlights and Headliners," Intown Club, Cleveland, Ohio
      - Mar. 25, B'nai B'rith Women, convention honoring Lady Bird Johnson, Washington, D.C.
      - Mar. 30, "Highlights and Headliners," Women's Press Club, St. Petersburg, Fla.
      - Apr. 22, Young Women's Christian Association, Fairfax, Va.
      - May 11, "Scholarships Build Bridges," PEO Sisterhood, Washington, D.C.
      - June 13, "The Fine Art of Creating Goodwill," General Federation of Women's Clubs, Boston, Mass.
      - June 20, National Foreign Policy Conference for Education Leaders, Washington, D.C.
      - June 22, "Human Rights Year," State Commissions on Status of Women Conference, Washington, D.C.
      - July 29, “Overseas with UNRRA–1945,” Women's National Press Club, Washington, D.C.
      - Nov. 20, Unesco meeting, Paris, France
      - Correspondence and miscellaneous speeches
    - 1970-1974, (2 folders)
  - Writings (Box 51)
    - Articles
      - “As We Remember Her,” tribute to Florence Jaffray Hurst Harriman, 1967
      - “Chez Bonnet,” unpublished article on Léon Blum, 1946
      - “A Congress to Win the War,” New Republic, 1942
      - “A Conversation with Eleanor [McGovern],” 1972
      - “Fifty Percent of the World,” Overseas, 1961-1962
      - “Her Interest Is People,” article on Lady Bird Johnson, Ladies' Home Journal, 1961-1964, undated
      - “Ilya Ehrenburg on American Writers,” New Republic, 1946
      - “Men and Women Studying Women,” Washington Post, 1971
      - Miscellaneous, 1937-1972, undated, (3 folders)
      - “Report on Germany,” 1952-1953
      - “The Role of a Woman's Organization in Cultural Diplomacy,” American Soroptimist, 1961-1962
      - “Sabbatical for the Second Sex,” 1965
      - “Senate Wives: Demands from All Sides,” Washington Post, 1971
      - State Department, 1961-1967
      - “Visitors Come to Observe Us As Well As Our Skills,” Washington Post, 1962
      - “The Voluntary Spirit in the Foreign Service,” Junior League of Baltimore Topics, 1965
      - “The Washington Kaleidoscope,” 1949, undated
      - “Washington Letters,” 1942-1946
      - White House restoration, 1949-1950
      - “Wives of Democratic Hopefuls Lend a Hand,” Christian Science Monitor, 1972
      - “A Woman for President?” 1963-1964
      - “Year of the Woman,” Christian Science Monitor, 1971-1972, undated, (1 folder); (2 folders) (Box 52)
    - Book reviews, 1948-1974, undated
    - Books
      - Atomic energy, unpublished picture book, 1946-1947, undated
      - By the Political Sea
        - Books reviews and published excerpts, 1970-1971
        - Correspondence with Doubleday and Co., 1968-1972
        - Letters of praise, 1970-1971, (2 folders)
      - “The Horrible Beautiful People,” correspondence concerning unpublished novel, 1951-1962
      - Georgetown, D.C., unpublished picture book, 1962-1968
      - “If You Came This Way,” unpublished novel, 1946-1947, (2 folders)
      - “The Little Mouse Said,” unpublished children's book, 1962-1966 (Box 53)
      - Novels, miscellaneous drafts and notes, 1946-1947, undated
      - “Protocol in Washington, D.C.,” unpublished, 1946-1952, undated
        - Correspondence and drafts
        - Notes and research material, (2 folders)
      - Roosevelt, Franklin D., unpublished picture book, 1947, undated
      - United Nations, unpublished picture book, 1946-1947
      - With or Without Roses See also Container 55, Poems
        - Book review and publicity, 1966-1967
        - Correspondence with publishers, 1966-1969, (2 folders)
        - Draft, undated
        - Letters of appreciation, 1966-1970
          - A-D
          - E-Z, (3 folders) (Box 54)
    - General correspondence
      - Literary agent, 1967-1968
      - Publishers, 1942-1962
    - Notes and fragments, 1945, undated
    - Opera libretto
      - Correspondence with composer David Diamond, 1971-1972, undated
      - Drafts, 1971-1973, undated, (2 folders)
    - Poetry
      - Correspondence
        - Letters of appreciation, 1948-1967, undated, (1 folder) (Box 55)
        - Publishers, 1948-1967, undated, (2 folders)
      - Poems See also Container 53, With or Without Roses
        - “Jiggery Pokery,” 1967-1968, undated
        - “Just Yesterday,” 1970-1971
        - Miscellaneous, 1967-1974, undated
    - Scripts for radio, television, and theater
      - “1952 Booms and Busts,” 1952
      - “The Lady Yields”
        - Correspondence, 1948-1958
        - Draft, undated
      - Miscellaneous, 1941-1957, undated
      - “When Witches Ride,” 1950
    - Short stories
      - “Born to Belong,” 1967
      - “The Day Off,” 1950
      - “The Heart Hides,” undated (Box 56)
      - “Mrs. Saunders' Christmas,” 1946
      - “My Sugar Plum,” undated
      - “Our Kind of Time,” 1948, undated
      - “Pre-Invasion Spring,” undated
      - “The Price of Wisdom,” undated
      - “The Spell,” 1945
      - “A Time for Living,” 1946
      - “The Time Has Come,” 1947
- Scrapbooks, 1945-1974 (Box 56)
  Scrapbooks containing clippings, photographs, mementos, and correspondence relating to the Democratic National Committee, State Department, Unesco, and Louchheim's public appearances and writings.
  Arranged chronologically. See Oversize.
  - See Oversize (Box 56)
- 1978 Addition, 1942-1977 (Box 56-61)
  Family papers, general correspondence, subject file, and speeches and writings.
  Arranged by type of material.
  - Family papers, Adele Joseph Scofield, 1947-1951 (Box 56)
  - General correspondence, 1961-1974
    - A-E, (5 folders)
    - F-L, (8 folders) (Box 57)
    - M-V See also Classified, (10 folders) (Box 58)
    - W-Z See also Classified, (3 folders) (Box 59)
  - Subject file
    - All Saints Church, Chevy Chase, Md., 1970-1973
    - Boggs, Hale, 1973
    - Contributions, 1966-1975
    - Folger Shakespeare Library, Washington, D.C., poetry reading, 1974-1975
    - Foreign service, 1961-1965
    - Georgetown University School of Foreign Service, Washington, D.C., board of visitors, 1971-1977
    - German Marshall Fund of the United States, 1973-1976
    - Johnson, Lyndon B.
      - Lyndon Baines Johnson Library, Austin, Tex., 1975
      - Lyndon Baines Johnson Memorial Grove, Washington, D.C., 1974-1976
    - Metropolitan Opera Guild, New York, N.Y., 1967
    - Miscellany, 1954-1977
    - Notebook, 1961-1974
    - Oral history interview, Harry S. Truman Library, Independence, Mo., 1975 (Box 60)
    - Personal file, 1942-1969 See also Classified
    - Photocopies of items in the family scrapbook, 1942-1953
    - Smith, Margaret Chase, 1972-1977
    - Society for a More Beautiful National Capital, 1973-1976
    - State Department, social calendar, 1960-1975
    - Unesco resignation, 1968-1969 See also Classified
    - Women's Lobby, 1973-1974
  - Speeches and writings file
    - Speeches
      - 1970, Dec. 10, Women's National Democratic Club
      - 1971
        - Jan. 12, Cosmopolitan Club, New York, N.Y.
        - Mar., Young Women's Christian Association, Washington, D.C.
      - 1972
        - Feb.
          - "Politics, the Effect of the Media," Young Women's Christian Association, Washington, D.C.
          - Untitled address, Young Women's Christian Association, Washington, D.C.
        - May 18, "From Rhetoric to Reality," Friends of the Arthur and Elizabeth Schlesinger Library, Cambridge, Mass.
        - Oct., Young Women's Christian Association, Washington, D.C.
        - Oct.-Nov., "The Purpose of Poets," Young Women's Christian Association, Washington, D.C., and All Saints Church, Chevy Chase, Md.
        - Nov. 1, Poetry Society of Virginia, Lynchburg, Va.
        - Nov. 14, "What Makes a Winner," Young Women's Christian Association, Washington, D.C.
        - circa 1972, "Leaks and Their Consequences," Georgetown University, Washington, D.C.
      - 1973
        - Mar. 22, "So Far, No Further"
        - Apr. 3, on women poets
        - May 21, Washington Society for Technical Communication, Washington, D.C.
      - Undated
        - "The Grub and the Glory"
        - Untitled speech on politics
        - Young Women's Christian Association, Washington, D.C.
    - Writings
      - By the Political Sea
        - Correspondence
          - Doubleday and Co., 1968-1972
          - Eccentrics, 1970-1974
          - General, 1969-1971
        - Outline and chapters, 1960-1968, undated
        - Publicity, 1970 (Box 61)
        - Research, notes, and drafts, 1955-1970, undated, (6 folders)
        - Speeches, 1970-1971
        - Workbook, 1968, undated
      - "The Latest Poll," Santa Rosa, Calif., News Herald, 1976
      - With or Without Roses, 1966-1971
- 1986 Addition, 1906-1985 (Box 61-75)
  General correspondence, subject file, speeches and writings file, and photographs.
  - General correspondence (Box 61)
    - "A" miscellaneous, 1969-1984, undated, (2 folders)
    - Bingham, Barry and Mary, 1974-1981
    - Blankfort, Michael, 1974-1981
    - Bolling, Richard, 1976-1983
    - Boorstin, Daniel J. and Ruth Frankel, 1974-1983 (Box 62)
    - "B" miscellaneous, 1975-1985, undated, (3 folders)
    - Cairns, Huntington, 1974-1979
    - Carter, Jimmy, 1976-1980
    - Crawford, Kenneth, 1974-1982
    - Culley, Perry and Harriet, 1973-1976, undated
    - "C-D" miscellaneous, 1968-1985, undated, (3 folders)
    - “E-F” miscellaneous, 1973-1985, undated, (3 folders) (Box 63)
    - Godwin, Dot and Peter, 1976-1979
    - Gordon, Ellie, 1979-1981
    - Guthrie, Stuart, undated
    - "G" miscellaneous, 1975-1985, undated
    - Hill, Tom, 1976-1981
    - Humphrey, Hubert H., 1976-1978
    - Humphrey, Muriel Buck, 1978
    - "H-I" miscellaneous, 1976-1984, undated, (3 folders)
    - Jellicoe, Geoffrey and Susan, 1975-1985 (Box 64)
    - Johnson, Lady Bird, 1971-1984
    - "J" miscellaneous, 1971-1985, undated
    - Kenworthy, E. W., 1977-1983
    - Kilgore, John, 1984-1985
    - "K" miscellaneous, 1975-1985, undated
    - Le Carré, John, 1977-1978
    - Limmer, Ruth, 1974-1981
    - “L” miscellaneous, 1973-1984, undated
    - Menuhin, Yehudi, 1974-1983
    - Meredith, William, 1979-1983
    - "M" miscellaneous, 1975-1985, undated, (2 folders)
    - “N-R” miscellaneous, 1967-1985, undated, (7 folders) (Box 65)
    - Smit, Leo, 1975-1979
    - Sohle, Grace, 1961-1982, (3 folders)
    - Symington, Stuart, 1972-1978 (Box 66)
    - "S" miscellaneous, 1975-1985, undated, (2 folders)
    - Treat, Rose, 1976-1977
    - Truman, Bess Wallace, 1970-1981
    - “T-Z” miscellaneous, 1970-1985, undated, (7 folders)
    - Unidentified correspondents, 1975-1985, undated
  - Subject file (Box 67)
    - Auden, W. H., 1978
    - Bayh, Birch, campaign, 1980
    - Bobbitt Poetry Prize, 1981
    - Bogan, Louise, 1948-1981
    - Center for Democratic Policy, 1981
    - Center for the Study of Democratic Institutions, 1977-1979
    - Clippings, circa 1950-1984, (2 folders)
    - Crawford, Ragsdale, 1977
    - Democratic Party, 1981-1982
    - Democrats for the 80's, 1980-1982
    - Douglas, William O., 1981 (Box 68)
    - Entertainment, 1970-1980
    - Ethical Culture Society, 1981
    - Federal Women's Award, 1973-1978
    - George Mason University, Fairfax, Va., 1980-1981
    - Georgetown University School of Foreign Service, Washington, D.C., 1972-1981
    - John F. Kennedy Center for the Performing Arts, Washington, D.C., poetry, 1979
    - John F. Kennedy Library, Boston, Mass., oral history interview, 1968, 1975
    - Kreps, Juanita, and Patricia Harris reception, 1973-1979
    - Letters to editors, 1972-1978
    - Library of Congress
      - Donation of papers, 1968-1981
      - Miscellany, 1969-1978
    - Magistrates, 1964-1975
    - Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Council for the Arts, Cambridge, Mass., 1976-1982
    - Mementos, 1963-1981 (Box 69)
    - Miscellany, 1980-1983
    - National Association for the Southern Poor, 1980-1981
    - National Collection of Fine Arts, Washington, D.C., 1972-1980
    - National Council on the Arts, 1973-1978
    - National Portrait Gallery, Washington, D.C.
      - Commission, 1974-1982, (2 folders)
      - Miscellany, 1974-1981
    - New Deal dinner, 1976-1977
    - Oral history interview, William E. Wiener Oral History Library, New York, N.Y., 1983
    - Presidential Inaugural Committee, 1961
    - Provincetown Fine Arts Work Center, Provincetown, Mass., 1980
    - Radcliffe College, Cambridge, Mass.
      - Arthur and Elizabeth Schlesinger Library on the History of Women in America
        - Correspondence
          - 1974-1977
          - 1978-1982 (Box 70)
        - Transcripts of interviews by Louchheim for Women in Federal Government Project, 1974, 1981-1982, (2 folders)
      - Miscellany, 1979
    - Roosevelt, Franklin D., centennial, 1981-1982
    - Rosemary Hall, Greenwich, Conn., The Rosemary Answer Book, 1920-1921
    - Smithsonian Institution, Washington, D.C., 1976-1982
    - United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration See also Containers 38-39, same heading
      - 1945, (5 folders)
      - 1946, undated, (4 folders) (Box 71)
  - Speech and writings file
    - Speeches
      - Ideas for, 1962-1975
      - Introductions, 1956-1981, (2 folders)
    - Writings
      - "The Little Red House"
        - Correspondence, 1976-1979
        - Drafts, 1976-1979, undated, (3 folders); (1 folder) (Box 72)
        - Research, 1934-1980, undated, (4 folders)
      - The Making of the New Deal
        - Drafts, 1982, undated, (5 folders); (24 folders) (Box 73)
        - Miscellany, 1982-1985
      - Miscellaneous articles, 1974-1984, undated (Box 74)
      - Poetry
        - Correspondence and readings, 1924, 1939, 1968-1984
        - Published poems, 1952-1980, (2 folders)
        - The Seeing Glass, 1979-1981
  - Miscellany
    - Photographs, 1906-1980, undated See also Oversize, (4 folders); (6 folders) (Box 75)
    - Sketches for book of children's poetry, undated
- 1997 Addition, 1942-1991 (Box 76-80)
  Journals, family and general correspondence, eulogies, and interviews.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - Correspondence (Box 76)
    - Family, circa 1953-1975
    - General, 1985-1988, undated
  - Eulogies, 1991
  - Interviews conducted by Louchheim, 1985-1986, undated
    - Astor, Brooke
    - Blum, Priscilla H.
    - Carlisle, Kitty
    - Furness, Betty
    - Lindsey, Mary P.
    - Marcus, Celine
    - Michel, Harriet
    - Miscellaneous correspondence
    - Motley, Constance Baker
    - Murch, Anna Crouse
    - Novac, Barbara
    - Polier, Justine Wise
    - Rifkind, Arlene
    - Schull, Diantha Dow
    - Sifton, Elisabeth
    - Tree, Marietta
    - Vanderbilt, Helen
    - Weiss, Nancy J.
  - Journals (Box 77)
    - 1942-1956, (9 folders)
    - 1957-1963, (8 folders) (Box 78)
    - 1964-1967, Oct., (10 folders) (Box 79)
    - 1967, Nov.-1981, June, (10 folders) (Box 80)
- 2010 Addition, 1940-1976 (Box 81)
  Political campaign buttons, a sticker, and plastic figure.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of candidate, slogan, or topic.
  - Campaign buttons and political memorabilia (Box 81)
    - Carter, Jimmy, 1976
    - Democratic Party, undated
    - Humphrey, Hubert H., 1968
    - “I Voted,” 1976
    - Johnson, Lyndon B., and Hubert H. Humphrey, 1964
    - Kennedy, John F., and Lyndon B. Johnson, 1960
    - McCarthy, Eugene, 1968
    - Nixon, Richard, 1972
    - Roosevelt, Franklin D., and Henry A. Wallace, 1940
    - Stevenson, Adlai, 1952-1956
    - Truman, Harry S., post-1953
- Classified, 1944-1970 (Box CL1)
  Correspondence, memoranda, telegrams, reports, minutes, personnel records, and lists.
  Organized and described according to the series, containers, and folders from which the items were removed.
  - General Correspondence (Box CL 1)
    - Carpenter, Liz, 1963-1968 (Container 3)
    - Humphrey, Hubert H., 1964 (Container 5)
    - Reischauer, Edwin O. and Haru Matsukata, 1962 (Container 7)
  - Subject File
    - Federal Women's Award
      - Study Group on Careers for Women, 1967 (Container 16)
    - Gandhi, Idira, state visits, 1962 (Container 18)
    - Johnson, Lady Bird
      - Correspondence concerning, 1964-1965 (Container 20)
    - State Department
      - Administrative file
        - Ambassadors and their wives, 1967 (Container 24)
        - Business advisors and consultants, 1965 (Container 24)
        - Crockett, William J., 1964 (Container 24)
        - General correspondence
          - A-R, 1966 (Container 26)
          - S-Z, 1967 (Container 27)
        - Hebrew University, Jerusalem, Israel, 1964 (Container 27)
        - Regional operations conferences
          - 1962, Bagiuio, Philippines (Container 30)
        - Reports and policy papers by Louchheim, undated (Container 30)
        - United States Advisory Commission on International Education and Cultural Affairs, 1968 (Container 31)
        - Women and minorities in foreign service, 1964 (Container 31)
        - Women appointees
          - Recommendations, 1964 (Container 31)
        - Women's programs, 1964 (Container 32)
        - Women's social and political lists, 1965-1968 (Container 32)
      - Bureau of Education and Cultural Affairs
        - Advisory Committee on International Books and Library Programs, 1968 (Container 32)
        - American Specialist Program, 1966-1968, undated (Containers 32-33)
        - Budget requests, 1967 (Container 33)
        - Exchange programs
          - Volunteers to America, 1966 (Container 34)
        - International Cooperation Year, 1966 (Container 34)
        - Re, Edward Domenic, 1968 (Container 34)
        - Reports, 1968 (Container 35)
        - Trips
          - 1962
            - Europe
              - Correspondence and arrangements, 1962 (Container 35)
              - Reports and follow-up, 1962 (Container 35)
            - Far East
              - Correspondence, 1962 (Container 35)
      - Office of Community Advisory Services
        - Reports and correspondence, 1967 (Container 36)
    - Unesco
      - Board members, 1968 (Container 37)
      - Fifteenth General Conference, Paris, France
        - Correspondence, 1968 (Container 38)
      - Personnel file, 1969 (Container 38)
      - State Department reports and memoranda, 1968-1969 (Container 38)
    - United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration
      - Meetings, memoranda, reports, and personnel file, 1944 (Container 38)
    - White House
      - Guest lists, 1963-1966 (Container 39)
    - Women
      - Project for Promoting Political Understanding Among German Women, 1963-1965 (Container 40)
      - United States-Soviet Union exchange program, 1963 (Container 40)
  - Speeches and Writings
    - Speaking engagements
      - Background material
        - Foreign policy, 1962 (Container 42)
  - 1978 Addition
    - General correspondence
      - M-V, 1970 (Container 58)
      - W-Z, 1968 (Container 59)
    - Subject file
      - Personal file, 1962-1968 (Container 60)
      - Unesco resignation, 1969 (Container 60)
- Oversize, 1945-1974 (Box OV 1-OV 25)
  Scrapbook, an autographed photograph of Louchheim and Lyndon B. Johnson, and prints.
  - Scrapbooks (Container 56) (Box OV 1)
    - Democratic National Committee
      - 1952, convention and campaign correspondence
      - 1952-1954, clippings and photographs (Box OV 2)
      - 1953-1959, clippings and convention photographs (Box OV 3)
      - 1954-1960, clippings and photographs (Box OV 4)
      - 1955, Democratic Women's Regional Conferences (Box OV 5)
        - Apr., Milwaukee, Wis.
        - Sept., Kansas City, Mo. (Box OV 6)
        - Oct. (Box OV 7)
          - Spokane, Wash.
          - Las Vegas, Nev. (Box OV 8)
      - 1956 (Box OV 9)
        - Democratic Women's Regional Conferences
          - Feb., Nashville, Tenn.
          - Mar., Atlantic City, N.J. (Box OV 10)
          - May, Dayton, Ohio (Box OV 11)
        - Democratic National Convention, Chicago, Ill., women's activities (Box OV 12)
      - 1958, Campaign Conference for Democratic Women Leaders, Washington, D.C. (Box OV 13)
      - 1959, campaign conferences (Box OV 14)
        - Cleveland, Ohio
        - Hartford, Conn. (Box OV 15)
      - 1960, campaign and election clippings (Box OV 16)
    - Miscellaneous (Box OV 17)
      - 1945-1967, photographs
      - 1961-1963, clippings and photographs (Box OV 18)
      - 1961-1968, White House, State Department, and national beautification programs (Box OV 19)
      - 1962-1968, State Department, Federal Women's Award, travel, photographs (Box OV 20)
      - 1963-1967, clippings (Box OV 21)
      - 1966, With or Without Roses, clippings and correspondence (Box OV 22)
      - 1967-1970, clippings related to Unesco and other topics (Box OV 23)
      - 1970-1974, clippings (Box OV 24)
    - 1986 Addition (Box OV 25)
      - Miscellany
        - Photographs, undated (Container 74)